Hey everyone! So, I'm pretty excited about the next sequence of videos that I'm doing.
嗨 大家好 一想到我正在做的下一个系列视频 我就很兴奋
They'll be about linear algebra,
下一个系列会讲线性代数
which as a lot of you know is one of those subjects that's
相信你们很多人都知道
required knowledge for just about any technical discipline,
有些学科几乎是一切专业学科的基石 而线性代数正是其中之一
but it's also I've noticed generally
但我也发现了
poorly understood by students taking it for the first time.
首次接触线性代数的学生通常对其所知甚少
A student might go through a class and learn how to compute lots of things like
学生可能会在课程里学到很多运算
matrix multiplication or the determinant or cross products,
比如矩阵乘法、行列式、向量积或特征值
which use the determinant or eigenvalues.
其中向量积又涉及行列式
But they might come out without really understanding
但学完后 他们很可能没有真正理解
why matrix multiplication is defined the way that it is.
为什么矩阵乘法要这么定义
Why the cross product has anything to do with
为什么向量积与行列式有关
the determinant or what an eigenvalue really represents.
特征值究竟代表着什么
Oftentimes, students end up well practiced in the numerical operations of
通常 学完那些课程后 学生虽然能熟练进行矩阵数字运算
matrices but are only vaguely aware of the geometric intuitions underlying it all.
但对运算背后的几何原理还是懵懵懂懂
But there's a fundamental difference between understanding linear algebra
可从数字层面上理解线性代数
on a numeric level and understanding it on a geometric level.
和从几何层面上理解是两个完全不同的概念
Each has its place but roughly speaking,
两者都有其意义 但总地来说
the geometric understanding is what let's you
从几何层面上理解线性代数
judge what tools to use to solve specific problems,
遇到问题 你就能针对性地找出解决工具
feel why they work,
你就能理解工具的原理
and know how to interpret the results.
知道如何分析结果
And the numeric understanding is what let's you
而从数字层面理解线性代数
actually carry through the application of those tools.
能让你真正应用这些工具
Now, if you learn linear algebra without getting
如果你学习了线性代数
a solid foundation in that geometric understanding,
但没有深刻理解其背后的几何原理
the problems can go unnoticed for a while until
短期内问题未必会出现
you've gone deeper into whatever field you happen to pursue.
但无论你在钻研什么领域 一旦你进一步深入 问题就会出现
Once you're in a class or a job for that matter that assumes fluency with linear algebra,
假设某个课程或职业默认你已经熟练掌握了线性代数
the way that your professors or your
在接触这个课程或职业时 你会发现 你的教授或同事
co-workers apply that field could seem like utter magic.
应用知识跟魔法似的
They'll very quickly know what the right tool to use
他们能快速确定使用工具
is and what the answer roughly looks like in
知道解决方案大概是什么样的
a way that would seem like computational wizardry if
如果你以为他们是在用数字思考问题的话
you assume that they're actually crunching all the numbers in their head.
那么你会认为他们前面的出色表现是因为他们会魔法
Here, as an analogy,
举个例子
imagine that when you first learned about the sine function in
回想你第一次接触三角学正弦函数的时候
trigonometry you were shown this infinite polynomial.
你学到了这个无穷多项式
This by the way is how your calculator evaluates the sine function.
顺便提一句 这是计算器求解正弦函数的途径
For homework, you might be asked to practice computing approximations of
写作业时 老师可能要求你
the sine function by plugging in various numbers
往方程里代入一些数字
to the formula and cutting it off at a reasonable point.
一直计算到某个恰当的项 从而求出正弦函数的近似值
And in fairness, let's say you had a vague idea that
公平点讲 假设你模糊地意识到
this was supposed to be related to triangles
正弦函数应该与三角形有关
but exactly how had never really been clear and was not the focus of the course.
但你不清楚它们的具体关系 课程也没有详细说明
Later on, if you took a physics course where
之后 你去上一个物理课
sines and cosines are thrown around left and right and
课上正弦函数和余弦函数漫天飞
people are able to tell pretty immediately how to apply
你的同学几乎立刻就知道要怎么应用这些函数
them and roughly what the sine of a certain value will be,
知道某个值的正弦函数大概会是多少
it would be pretty intimidating, wouldn't it?
你会不会觉得很惶恐？
It would make it seem like the only people who are cut
好像那些精通物理的人
out for physics are those with computers for
脑子都跟高速运转的计算机似的
brains and you would feel unduly slow or dumb for taking so long on each problem.
而你却又慢又迟钝 一个问题都要处理很久
It's not that different with linear algebra.
线性代数的学习过程也会出现类似的问题
And luckily, just as with trigonometry,
好在和三角学一样
there are a handful of intuitions,
线性代数大多数知识背后
visual intuitions, underlying much of the subject.
都有一些原理 视觉性的原理
And unlike the trig example,
与三角学不同的是
the connection between the computation and
线性代数的运算与这些视觉原理的关系
these visual intuitions is typically pretty straightforward.
通常都很简单明了
And when you digest these and really
等你消化了这些知识
understand the relationship between the geometry and the numbers,
真正理解了几何图形与数字之间的关系
the details of the subject as well as how it's used in
那线性代数的细节和应用
practice start to feel a lot more reasonable.
就慢慢变得合理起来了
In fairness, most professors do make an effort to convey that geometric understanding.
说句公道话 大多数教授在讲解几何原理时 已经很用心了
The sine example is a little extreme.
正弦函数那个例子夸张了些
But I do think that a lot of courses have students spending
但我的确觉得很多课程让学生花太多时间
a disproportionate amount of time on the numerical side of things,
在数字层面上了
especially given that in this day and age we almost always get computers
特别是今时今日 我们基本都是让计算机来处理这个层面的问题的
to handle that half while in practice humans worry about the conceptual half.
而人类自己则负责处理概念层面的问题
So, this brings me to the upcoming videos.
因此我萌生了做这系列视频的想法
The goal is to create a short,
我想做一个简单的系列视频
watchable series animating those intuitions from the basics of
将这些原理做成动画
vectors up through the core topics that make up the essence of linear algebra.
讲解上至线性代数核心 下至向量基础的知识
I'll do what I can to keep things well paced throughout
我会尽可能平衡课程节奏
but it's hard to simultaneously account for
但要同时考虑各人的知识背景
different people's different backgrounds and levels of comfort so I
和舒适区是很难的
do encourage you to readily pause and ponder if you feel that it's necessary.
所以建议你根据自己的需要 随时暂停以便思考
Actually, I'd give that same advice for
实际上 同样的建议
watching any math video even if it doesn't feel too
也适用于其它数学视频
quick since the thinking that you do on
哪怕你不觉得视频节奏太快 毕竟独立思考
your own time is where all the learning really happens, don't you think?
才能真正学到知识 你觉得呢？
So with that is an introduction, I'll see you next video.
好了 介绍完毕 下个视频见